Pat Mitchell: So I was thinking about female friendship a lot,
بات ميتشيل: لقد كنت أفكر كثيرا حول صداقات الإناث،
and by the way, these two women,
وبالمناسبة، هاتان السيدتان،
I'm very honored to say,
وأفتخر بالقول،
have been my friends for a very long time, too.
هما صديقتايا منذ زمن طويل، أيضا.
Jane Fonda: Yes we have.
جين فوندا: أجل نحن كذلك.
PM: And one of the things that I read about female friendship
بات: وأحد الأمورالتي قرأتها عن الصداقة بين الإناث
is something that Cervantes said.
هو شيْء قاله سيرفانتيس.
He said, "You can tell a lot about someone,"
لقد قال: "يمكنك معرفة الكثير عن شخص ما،"
in this case a woman,
في هذه الحالة إمرأة،
"by the company that she keeps."
"من الرفقة التي تبقيها."
So let's start with --
لنبدأ مع --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
JF: We're in big trouble.
جين فوندا: نحن في مأزق كبير.
Lily Tomlin: Hand me one of those waters,
ليلي توملين: أعطيني أحد كؤوس المياه.
I'm extremely dry.
أنا عطشة جدا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
JF: You're taking up our time.
جين فوندا: أنت تضيعين وقتنا.
We have a very limited --
لدينا وقت محدد جدا--
LT: Just being with her sucks the life out of me.
ليلي توملين: يقتلني مجرد أن أكون برفقتها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
JF: You ain't seen nothing yet.
جين فوندا: لم تري شيئا بعد.
Anyway -- sorry.
على أي حال -- آسفة.
PM: So tell me, what do you look for in a friend?
بات ميتشيل: إذا أخبريني، ما هي مواصفات الصديق التي تبحثين عنها؟
LT: I look for someone who has a sense of fun,
ليلي توملين: أبحث عن أحد لديه حس الفكاهة،
who's audacious,
وأن يكون شجاعا،
who's forthcoming, who has politics,
ويكون صريحا، لديه سياسات،
who has even a small scrap of passion for the planet,
أن يكون على الأقل لديه ذرة حب للكوكب،
someone who's decent, has a sense of justice
شخص لطيف، عادل
and who thinks I'm worthwhile.
ويعتقد أنني جديرة بالإهتمام.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
JF: You know, I was thinking this morning,
جين فوندا: أتعلمين، لقد كنت أفكر في هذا الصباح،
I don't even know what I would do without my women friends.
لا أعلم ما كنت لأفعل بدون صديقاتي الإناث.
I mean it's, "I have my friends, therefore I am."
أنا أعني، " بما أنه لديا أصدقائي, إذن أنا موجودة."
LT: (Laughter)
ليلي توملين: (ضحك)
JF: No, it's true.
جين فوندا: لا، هذه الحقيقة.
I exist because I have my women friends. They --
أنا موجودة لأنه عندي صديقاتي الإناث. هن--
You're one of them.
أنت واحدة منهن.
I don't know about you. But anyway --
لا أعلم بشأنك. لكن في كل الأحوال--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You know, they make me stronger, they make me smarter,
أتعلمين، يجعلونني أقوى، ويجعلونني أذكى،
they make me braver.
ويجعلونني أشجع.
They tap me on the shoulder when I might be in need of course-correcting.
يربتون على كتفي عندما أحتاج الى تصحيح مسار.
And most of them are a good deal younger than me, too.
وأغلبهم أصغر مني سنا، أيضا.
You know? I mean, it's nice -- LT: Thank you.
أتعلمين؟ أعني، هذا شيْ لطيف-- ليلي توملين: شكرا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
JF: No, I do, I include you in that, because listen, you know --
جين فوندا: أنا كذلك بالفعل، أنا اشملك بهذا، لأنه اسمعي, أتعلمين--
it's nice to have somebody still around to play with and learn from
أنه لشيء لطيف أن يكون أحد حولك لتلعبي معه وتتعلمي منه
when you're getting toward the end.
عندما تتجهين للنهاية.
I'm approaching -- I'll be there sooner than you.
أنا أقترب-- سأكون هناك أسرع منك.
LT: No, I'm glad to have you parallel aging alongside me.
ليلي توملين: لا، أنا سعيدة لأنك تتقدّمين في السنّ وأنت بجانبي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
JF: I'm showing you the way.
جين فوندا: أنا أظهر لك الطريق.
LT: Well, you are and you have.
ليلي توملين: حسنا، أنت كذلك وعليك ذلك.
PM: Well, as we grow older,
بات ميتشيل: حسنا، عندما نتقدّم في العمر،
and as we go through different kinds of life's journeys,
وبينما نخوض مراحل مختلفة في حياتنا،
what do you do to keep your friendships vital and alive?
ماذا تفعلين لتبقي صداقاتك حية؟
LT: Well you have to use a lot of --
ليلي توملين: عليك أن تستخدمي الكثير من--
JF: She doesn't invite me over much, I'll tell you that.
جين فوندا: هي لا تدعوني إلى منزلها كثيرا، ها أنا اقول لك.
LT: I have to use a lot of social media --
ليلي توملين: يجب عليا أن أستخدم مواقع التواصل الإجتماعي كثيرا--
You be quiet now. And so --
أسكتي أنت الآن. و--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
LT: And I look through my emails, I look through my texts
ل.ت: أبحث في البريد الالكتروني, وفي رسائلي
to find my friends,
لأجد اصدقائي،
so I can answer them as quickly as possible,
لأجيبهم بأسرع وقت ممكن،
because I know they need my counsel.
لأنني أعلم أنهم بحاجة لاستشارتي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They need my support,
يحتاجون دعمي،
because most of my friends are writers, or activists, or actors,
لأن معظم أصدقائي هم إما كاتبون، أو ناشطون، أو ممثلون،
and you're all three ...
وأنتم الثلاثة...
and a long string of other descriptive phrases,
وسلسلة طويلة من العبارات الوصفية الأخرى،
and I want to get to you as soon as possible,
وأريد أن أصل لك بأسرع وقت ممكن،
I want you to know that I'm there for you.
أريدك أن تعلمي أنني سأكون بجوارك دائما.
JF: Do you do emojis?
ج.ف: هل تقومين بالايموجيس؟
LT: Oh ... JF: No?
ل.ت: اوه... ج.ف: لا؟
LT: That's embarrassing. JF: I'm really into emojis.
ل.ت: هذا محرج. ج.ف: أنا أحبهم جدا.
LT: No, I spell out my --
ل.ت: لا, أنا أوضح--
I spell out my words of happiness and congratulations,
أنا أوضح كلماتي الدالة على السعادة والتهاني،
and sadness.
والحزن،
JF: You spell it right out --
ج.ف: أجل وضحيها--
LT: I spell it, every letter.
ل.ت: أنا أوضحها، كل حرف.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
JF: Such a purist.
ج.ف: أنك لشخص طاهر.
You know, as I've gotten older,
أتعلمين، عندما كبرت في السن،
I've understood more the importance of friendships,
تعلمت المزيد عن أهمية الصداقة،
and so, I really make an effort
وهكذا، أنا حقا أبذل جهد
to reach out and make play dates -- not let too much time go by.
لأصل وأضع المواعيد-- حتى لا أترك الوقت يذهب سدى.
I read a lot
أنا أقرأ كثيرا
so, as Lily knows all too well,
وهكذا، كما تعلم ليلي جيدا،
my books that I like, I send to my friends.
كتبي التي أحبها، أرسلها لأصدقائي.
LT: When we knew we would be here today
ل.ت: عندما علمنا أننا سنكون هنا اليوم
you sent me a lot of books about women, female friendships,
أرسلت لي الكثير من الكتب عن النساء، وصداقات النساء،
and I was so surprised to see how many books,
وتفاجأت عندما رأيت العدد الكبير من الكتب،
how much research has been done recently --
والأبحاث التي جرت حديثا--
JF: And were you grateful? LT: I was grateful.
ج.ف: وهل كنت ممتنة؟ ل.ت: أجل لقد كنت كذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
PM: And --
ب.م: و--
LT: Wait, no, it's really important because this is another example
ل.ت: انتظري، لا، إنه مهم جدا لأنه مثال آخر
of how women are overlooked, put aside, marginalized.
لعدد النساء اللواتي يتم التغاضي عنهن، يوضعون جانبا، يتم تهميشهن.
There's been very little research done on us,
لقد كان هنالك عدد قليل من الأبحاث حولنا،
even though we volunteered lots of times.
بالرغم من تطوعنا في الكثير من الأحيان.
JF: That's for sure.
ج.ف: هذا أكيد.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
LT: This is really exciting, and you all will be interested in this.
ل.ت: هذا مثير جدا، وجميعكم ستهتمون بهذا.
The Harvard Medical School study has shown
كلية الطب في جامعة هارفرد وجدت
that women who have close female friendships
أن النساء اللواتي لديهن صداقات مقربة مع نساء أخريات
are less likely to develop impairments --
هم أقل عرضة أقل لتطور الإعتلالات--
physical impairments as they age,
والأمراض الجسدية عنما يتقدمون في السن،
and they are likely to be seen to be living much more vital, exciting --
ولديهن أحتمال أكبر في عيش حياة أكثر حيوية, مثيرة--
JF: And longer --
ج.ف: وأطول--
LT: Joyful lives.
ل.ت: حياة ممتعة.
JF: We live five years longer than men.
ج.ف: نحن نعيش خمس سنوات أكثر من الرجال.
LT: I think I'd trade the years for joy.
ل.ت: اظن أنني مستعدة لتبديل هذه السنوات للمتعة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
LT: But the most important part is they found --
ل.ت: لكن أهم جزء هو أنهم وجدوا--
the results were so exciting and so conclusive --
أن النتائج كانت مثيرة وحاسمة جدا--
the researchers found
وجد الباحثون
that not having close female friends is detrimental to your health,
أن عدم وجود صديقات أناث لشخص ما مضر لصحته
as much as smoking or being overweight.
مثل التدخين والوزن الزائد.
JF: And there's something else, too --
ج.ف: وهناك شيئا آخر, أيضا--
LT: I've said my part, so ...
ل.ت: لقد قلت الجزء الخاص بي , لذلك...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
JF: OK, well, listen to my part, because there's an additional thing.
ج.ف: أجل, حسنا، استمعي للجزء الخاص بي، لأنه يوجد أمر إضافي.
Because they only -- for years, decades --
لأنهم فقط -- لسنوات, لعقود--
they only researched men when they were trying to understand stress,
قاموا بأبحاث على الرجال فقط لفهم ظاهرة التوتر،
only very recently have they researched what happens to women when we're stressed,
فقط مؤخرا بحثوا عن أعراض التوتر للنساء،
and it turns out that when we're stressed -- women,
كانت الإستنتاجات أننا عندما نتوتر--النساء،
our bodies get flooded by oxytocin.
يغمر الأوكسيتوسين أجسادنا.
Which is a feel-good, calming, stress-reducing hormone.
وهو الهرمون الذي يقوم بتهدئتنا وتقليل توترنا.
Which is also increased when we're with our women friends.
وهو نفس الهرمون الذي يزداد إفرازه عندما نكون برفقة صديقاتنا الأناث.
And I do think that's one reason why we live longer.
وأنا أعتقد أنه أحد الأسباب التي تجعلنا نعيش أكثر.
And I feel so bad for men because they don't have that.
لذا أشعر بالسوء تجاه الرجال لأنهم لا يملكون ذلك.
Testosterone in men diminishes the effects of oxytocin.
هرمون تستوستيرون الذي ينتجه الرجال يقلل عمل الأوكسيتوسين.
LT: Well, when you and I and Dolly made "9 to 5" ...
ل.ت: حسنا, عندما أنا وأنت ودولي صنعنا "9 ل 5"...
JF: Oh --
ج.ف: أوه--
LT: We laughed, we did, we laughed so much,
ل.ت: لقد ضحكنا، أجل، ضحكنا كثيرا،
we found we had so much in common and we're so different.
وجدنا الكثير من الأمور المشتركة بيننا مع أننا مختلفات جدا.
Here she is, like Hollywood royalty,
ها هي، مثل ملوك هوليوود،
I'm like a tough kid from Detroit,
أنا أشبه طفل حازم من ديترويت،
[Dolly's] a Southern kid from a poor town in Tennessee,
[دولي] مثل طفل جنوبي من مدينة فقيرة في ولاية تينيسي،
and we found we were so in sync as women,
ووجدنا أننا متزامنات جدا كنساء،
and we must have --
ويجب علينا--
we laughed -- we must have added at least a decade onto our lifespans.
ضحكنا-- يجب علينا إضافة عقد إلى حياتنا.
JF: I think -- we sure crossed our legs a lot.
ج.ف: أنا أعتقد-- أننا بالتأكيد وضعنا ساق على الأخرى كثيرا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If you know what I mean.
إذا فهمتم قصدي.
LT: I think we all know what you mean.
ل.ت: أعتقد أننا جميعا فهمنا ما تعنيه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
PM: You're adding decades to our lives right now.
ب.م: أنت تضيفين عقودا إلى أعمارنا الآن.
So among the books that Jane sent us both to read on female friendship
بين الكتب التي أرسلتها جين لنا لنقرأها عن صداقات النساء
was one by a woman we admire greatly, Sister Joan Chittister,
كان هناك كتاب لامرأة نحبها كثيرا، ألاخت جون تشيتستير،
who said about female friendship
التي قالت عن صداقات النساء
that women friends are not just a social act,
أن الصداقات بين النساء ليس مجرد أمر أجتماعي،
they're a spiritual act.
بل إنه أمر روحاني.
Do you think of your friends as spiritual?
هل ترين أن أصدقائك روحانيين؟
Do they add something spiritual to your lives?
هل يضيفون أمر روحاني لحياتك؟
LT: Spiritual -- I absolutely think that.
ل.ت: روحاني-- أنا أعتقد ذلك بالتأكيد.
Because -- especially people you've known a long time,
لأن -- خاصة الأشخاص الذين تعرفينهم منذ زمن
people you've spent time with --
الأشخاص الذين قضيت وقت معهم--
I can see the spiritual essence inside them,
يمكنني أن أرى الجوهر الروحاني بداخلهم،
the tenderness, the vulnerability.
الرقة، الضعف.
There's actually kind of a love, an element of love in the relationship.
في الحقيقة هناك نوع من الحب، عنصر للحب في العلاقة.
I just see deeply into your soul.
أنا فقط أنظر بعمق داخل أرواحكم.
PM: Do you think that, Jane --
ب.م: هل تعتقدين أنّ، جين--
LT: But I have special powers.
ل.ت: لدي قوى أستثنائية.
JF: Well, there's all kinds of friends.
ج.ف: حسنا، هناك أنواع من الأصدقاء.
There's business friends, and party friends,
هناك أصدقاء للعمل، وأصدقاء للاحتفال،
I've got a lot of those.
لدي الكثير من هذا النوع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But the oxytocin-producing friendships have ...
لكن الصداقات التي تفرز الأوكسيتوسين...
They feel spiritual because it's a heart opening, right?
هم يشعرون بالروحانية لأنه يجعل قلبهم ينفتح، أليس كذلك؟
You know, we go deep. And --
أنت تعلمين، نحن نرى بعمق. و--
I find that I shed tears a lot with my intimate friends.
لقد وجدت أنني أذرف الدموع كثيرا مع أصدقائي المقربين.
Not because I'm sad but because I'm so touched and inspired by them.
ليس لأنني حزينة بل لأنني أشعر بأنني ملهمة كثيرا معهم.
LT: And you know one of you is going to go soon.
ل.ت: وأنتن تعلمن أن إحداكن ستذهب قريبا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
PM: Well, two of us are sitting here, Lily, which one are you talking about?
ب.م: حسنا، أثنتان منا تجلسان هنا، ليلي، عن أي واحدة منا تتكلمين؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I always think, when women talk about their friendships,
وأنا أفكر دائما، عندما تتكلم النساء عن صداقاتهن،
that men always look a little mystified.
يبدو الرجال دائما محتارون.
What are the differences, in your opinion,
ما هي الفروق، في رأيك،
between men friendships and women friendships?
بين صداقات النساء وصداقات الرجال؟
JF: There's a lot of difference,
ج.ف: توجدالعديد من الفروق,
and I think we have to have a lot of empathy for men --
وأنا أعتقد أنه علينا التعاطف مع الرجال--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
that they don't have what we have.
بما أنهم لا يملكون ما نملك نحن.
Which I think may be why they die sooner.
والذي أعتقد أنه سبب موتهم المبكر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I have a lot of compassion for men,
أنا أشفق كثيرا على الرجال،
because women, no kidding, we --
لأن النساء، بدون مزح، نحن--
women's relationships, our friendships are full disclosure, we go deep.
صداقات النساء، صداقاتنا مليئة بالإكتشافات، نحن نبحث بعمق.
They're revelatory.
إنها علاقات كاشفة.
We risk vulnerability -- this is something men don't do.
نحن نعرض أنفسنا للضعف، هذا شيء لا يقوم به الرجال.
I mean how many times have I asked you, "Am I doing OK?"
أنا أعني كم مرة سألتك، "هل أقوم بعمل جيد؟"
"Did I really screw up there?"
"هل أخفقت بهذا الشيء؟"
PM: You're doing great.
ب.م: لقد قمت بعمل عظيم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
JF: But I mean, we ask questions like that
ج.ف: أنا أعني، نحن نسأل أسئلة كهذه
of our women friends,
لصديقاتنا النساء،
and men don't.
والرجال لا يفعلون ذلك.
You know, people describe women's relationships as face-to-face,
أتعلمين، الناس تصف علاقات النساء كوجه لوجه،
whereas men's friendships are more side-by-side.
بينما علاقات الرجال مثل طرف لطرف.
LT: I mean most of the time men don't want to reveal their emotions,
ل.ت: أنا أعني، في أغلب الأوقات لا يريد الرجال كشف مشاعرهم،
they want to bury deeper feelings.
يريدون دفن مشاعرهم العميقة.
I mean, that's the general, conventional thought.
أنا أعني، هذا عامة، فكرة تقليدية.
They would rather go off in their man cave and watch a game or hit golf balls,
يفضلون أن يذهبوا إلى كهفهم ومشاهدة مباراة أو لعب الغولف،
or talk about sports, or hunting, or cars or have sex.
أو التحدث عن الرياضة، أو الاصطياد، أوالسيارات أو إقامة علاقة.
I mean, it's just the kind of -- it's a more manly behavior.
أنا أعني، إنه نوع-- إنه تصرف ذكوري.
JF: You meant -- LT: They talk about sex.
ج.ف: أنت تعنين-- ل.ت: أنهم يتكلمون عن العلاقات.
I meant they might have sex
أعني أنه من الممكن أن يقيموا علاقة
if they could get somebody in their man cave to --
إذا أستطاعوا إدخال أحد الى كهفهم الذكوري--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
JF: You know something, though, that I find very interesting --
ج.ف: أتعلمين أمر، بالرغم, من أني أعتقد أنه مثير للاهتمام --
and again, psychologists didn't know this until relatively recently --
ومجددا، خبيرو النفس لم يعلموا هذا الأمر إلا مؤخرا--
is that men are born every bit as relational as women are.
أن الرجال خلقوا ولديهم القدر ذاته من العلاقات مثل النساء.
If you look at films of newborn baby boys and girls,
إذا نظرت إلى الأفلام عن الأولاد والبنات الذين ولدوا حديثا،
you'll see the baby boys just like the girls,
ستلاحظين أن الأطفال الذكور مثلهم مثل الإناث،
gazing into their mother's eyes,
يحدقون إلى أعين أمهم،
you know, needing that relational exchange of energy.
تعلمين يحتاجون هذه العلاقة المتبادلة من الطاقة،
When the mother looks away, they could see the dismay on the child,
عندما تنظر الأم بعيدا، يمكنك رؤية الخوف على الطفل،
even the boy would cry.
حتى يمكن للولد أن يبكي.
They need relationship.
يحتاجون للعلاقة.
So the question is why, as they grow older, does that change?
إذن السؤال هو لماذا، عندما يكبرون، يتغير ذلك؟
And the answer is patriarchal culture,
والإجابة هي الثقافة الأبوية،
which says to boys and young men
والتي تقول للأطفال والشباب أهميّة
that to be needing of relationship, to be emotional with someone is girly.
الحاجة للعلاقة، وتكوين عاطفة مع أحد هو شيء أنثوي.
That a real man doesn't ask directions or express a need,
وأن الرجل الحقيقي لا يسأل عن الأتجاهات أو يعبر عن حاجته،
they don't go to doctors if they feel bad.
لا يذهبون لاستشارة الأطباء عند شعورهم بالمرض.
They don't ask for help.
لا يطلبون المساعدة.
There's a quote that I really like,
هناك اقتباس أحبه كثيرا،
"Men fear that becoming 'we' will erase his 'I'."
"الرجال يخافون أن التحول ل 'نحن' سيمحي ال 'أنا' خاصتهم."
You know, his sense of self.
أنت تعلمين، شعوره بذاته.
Whereas women's sense of self has always been kind of porous.
بينما شعور المرأة بذاتها كان دائما مثل نوع من المسامي.
But our "we" is our saving grace,
لكن ال "نحن" عندنا هي بمثابة الرحمة التي تنقذنا،
it's what makes us strong.
هي التي تجعلنا أقوياء.
It's not that we're better than men,
ليس أننا أقضل من الرجال،
we just don't have our masculinity to prove.
إنما فقط أنه ليس علينا أثبات رجولتنا.
LT: And, well --
ل.ت: و، حسنا --
JF: That's a Gloria Steinem quote.
ج.ف: هذا كلام غلوريا ستاينم.
So we can express our humanity -- LT: I know who Gloria Steinem is.
أننا نستطيع التعبير عن إنسانيتنا -- ل.ت: أنا أعلم من تكون.
JF: I know you know who she is, but I think it's a --
ج.ف: أنا أعلم أنك تعلمين من هي، لكنني أعتقد أنه --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
No, but it's a great quote, I think.
لا، لكنني أعتقد أنه كلام عظيم.
We're not better than men, we just don't have our masculinity to prove.
لسنا أفضل من الرجال، لكن كل ما في الأمر أنه ليس علينا أثبات رجولتنا.
And that's really important.
وهذا شيء مهم جدا.
LT: But men are so inculcated in the culture
ل.ن: لكن الرجال منغمسين جدا في الحضارة
to be comfortable in the patriarchy.
ليكونوا مرتاحين بالمجتمع الأبوي.
And we've got to make something different happen.
وعلينا إحداث تغيير.
JF: Women's friendships are like a renewable source of power.
ج.ف: علاقات النساء هي مصدر طاقة قابل للتجدد.
LT: Well, that's what's exciting about this subject.
ل.ت: وهذا ما يجعل هذا الموضوع مثيرا للاهتمام.
It's because our friendships --
لأنه صداقاتنا--
female friendships are just a hop to our sisterhood,
صداقاتنا مع بعض هي أمل لعلاقتنا الأخوية،
and sisterhood can be a very powerful force,
والأخوية هي مصدر قوي للقوة،
to give the world --
لإعطاء العالم --
to make it what it should be --
لجعله كما يجب أن يكون --
the things that humans desperately need.
الأمور التي يحتاجها الناس بشدة.
PM: It is why we're talking about it,
ب.م: لهذا السبب نحن نتكلم عنها،
because women's friendships are,
لأن صداقات النساء،
as you said, Jane,
كما قلت، جين،
a renewable source of power.
مصدر طاقة قابل للتجديد.
So how do we use that power?
إذن كيف نستعمل هذة الطاقة؟
JF: Well, women are the fastest growing demographic in the world,
ج.ف: حسنا، النساء هم أسرع إنتشارا في العالم ديموغرافيا،
especially older women.
خاصة النساء الأكبر سنا.
And if we harness our power, we can change the world.
وإذا قمنا باستغلال طاقتنا، يمكننا تغيير العالم.
And guess what? We need to.
واحزري ماذا؟ نحن بحاجة لذلك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And we need to do it soon.
وعلينا فعل ذلك قريبا.
And one of the things that we need to do --
وأحد الأمور التي نحتاج لعملها--
and we can do it as women --
ونستطيع فعل ذلك كنساء--
for one thing, we kind of set the consumer standards.
نحن نقوم بتحديد معايير المستهلك.
We need to consume less.
نحن بحاجة لاستهلاك أقل.
We in the Western world need to consume less
نحن في العالم الغربي بحاجة لاستهلاك أقل
and when we buy things, we need to buy things that are made locally,
وعندما نشتري الأشياء، علينا شراء الاشياء التي صنعت محليا،
when we buy food, we need to buy food that's grown locally.
عندما نشتري الطعام، علينا شراء ذلك الطعام الذي زرع محليا.
We are the ones that need to get off the grid.
نحن من علينا أن نخرج من الشبكة.
We need to make ourselves independent from fossil fuels.
علينا أن نتوقف عن استخدام النفط الأحفوري.
And the fossil fuel companies --
وشركات النفط الأحفوري--
the Exxons and the Shell Oils and those bad guys --
اكسون وزيوت القشرة وأولئك الأشرار--
cause they are --
لأنهم --
are going to tell us that we can't do it without going back to the Stone Age.
سيقولون لنا أنه لا يمكننا فعل ذلك دون العودة للعصر الحجري.
You know, that the alternatives just aren't quite there yet,
أنت تعلمين، أن البدائل لا تتوفر بعد،
and that's not true.
وهذا غير صحيح.
There are countries in the world right now
هناك دول في العالم الآن
that are living mostly on renewable energy and doing just fine.
يعيشون على طاقة قابلة للتجدد وهم بخير.
And they tell us that if we do wean ourselves from fossil fuel
ويخبروننا أنه إذا تخلينا عن النفط الأحفوري
that we're going to be back in the Stone Age,
سنعود بأنفسنا إلى العصر الحجري،
and in fact, if we begin to use renewable energy,
وفي الحقيقة، إذا بدأنا باستعمال الطاقة المتجددة،
and not drill in the Arctic, and not drill --
وليس حفرة في القطب الجنوبي، وليس حفرة--
LT: Oh, boy.
ل.ت: أوه، ولدي.
JF: And not drill in the Alberta tar sands --
ج.ف: وليس الحفرة في رمال ألبيرتا --
Right.
صحيح.
That we will be --
سكون --
there will be more democracy and more jobs and more well-being,
سيكون هناك المزيد من الديموقراطية والمزيد من الوظائف والمزيد من السعادة،
and it's women that are going to lead the way.
والنساء سيكن من يقود الطريق.
LT: Maybe we have the momentum to start a third-wave feminist movement
ل.ت: يبدو أنه لدينا قوة الدفع لبدأ موجة ثالثة من الحركة النسوية.
with our sisterhood around the world,
مع أخواتنا في العالم،
with women we don't see, women we may never meet,
مع نساء لا نراها، ويمكن أن لا نقابلها أبدا،
but we join together that way,
لكننا ننضم معا في هذه الطريق.
because --
لأنه --
Aristotle said --
قال أرتيستول --
most people --
غالبية الناس --
people would die without male friendships.
يمكن للناس أن تموت بدون صداقات ذكورية.
And the operative word here was "male."
والكلمة الفعالة هنا هي "ذكر."
Because they thought that friendships should be between equals
لأنهم اعتقدوا أن الصداقات يجب أن تكون مع ناس تساويهم
and women were not considered equal --
وهم لا يعتبرون النساء مساوية لهم --
JF: They didn't think we had souls even, the Greeks.
ج.ف: هم حتى لم يروا أنه لدينا أرواح، اليونانين.
LT: No, exactly. That shows you just how limited Aristotle was.
ل.ت: بالتأكيد، هذا يظهر لك كم كان أرتيستول محدود الفكر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And wait, no, here's the best part.
انتظروا، لا، إليكم أفضل جزء.
It's like, you know, men do need women now.
إنه مثال, تعلمون، أن الرجال بحاجة للنساء الآن.
The planet needs women.
الكوكب بحاجة للنساء.
The US Constitution needs women.
دستور الولايات المتحدة بحاجة للنساء.
We are not even in the Constitution.
ونحن لسنا موجودات في الدستور حتى.
JF: You're talking about the Equal Rights Amendment.
ج.ف: أنت تتكلمين عن تعديل حقوق المساواة.
LT: Right.
ل.ت: صحيح.
Justice Ginsberg said something like --
قال غينسبرغ أن المساواة مثل --
every constitution that's been written since the end of World War II
كل دستور كان قد كتب منذ انتهاء الحرب العالمية الثانية
included a provision that made women citizens of equal stature,
شمل قانون يجعل النساء في مكانة متساوية،
but ours does not.
لكن قانوننا لم يقم بذلك.
So that would be a good place to start.
لذلك هذا سيكون مكان جيد للبدء فيه.
Very, very mild --
جدا، جدا معتدل --
JF: Right.
ج.ف: صحيح.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And gender equality, it's like a tide,
والمساواة بين الجنسين، يشبه المد والجزر،
it would lift all boats, not just women.
سيرفع كل القوارب، ليس فقط النساء.
PM: Needing new role models on how to do that.
ب.م: نحتاج لقدوة جديدة لكيفية فعل هذا.
How to be friends,
كيف نكون أصدقاء،
how to think about our power in different ways,
كيف نرى طاقاتنا في طرق مختلفة،
as consumers,
كمستهلكين،
as citizens of the world,
كمواطنين في العالم،
and this is what makes Jane and Lily
وهذا ما يجعل جيني وليلي،
a role model of how women can be friends --
قدوة لكيفية تكون النساء لصداقات--
for a very long time,
لمدة طويلة،
and even if they occasionally disagree.
وحتى إن كانتا تختلفان من وقت لآخر.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
Thank you both.
شكرا لكما الإثنتان.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
JF: Thanks.
ج.ف: شكرا.
LT: Thank you.
ل.ت: شكرا لك.
JF: Thank you.
ج.ف: شكرا لك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)